<Document>
  # Arresting Procedures

  Should an Officer order an arrest for a crime, MPs/Law Enforcement MUST arrest that person.

 ## Arresting a Suspect
  - Take down the Suspect if they resist and securely restrain them.
  - Non-lethal force must be used unless the suspect is armed with a lethal weapon and has shown intent to use it.
  - Move the Suspect to a holding cell.

## Command Arrests
 When arresting a member of command (CO, XO, JOs, etc) a facsimile must sent to the marshal office before hand with a DETAILED report with reasoning. A response is not required to proceed with the arrest. Once a fax has been sent the CMP (if presents) must be present for the arrest and one other MP. The command member must be read their rights in its entirety and if they are the commander of the operation they are given 10 minutes to hand over command properly. This may be EXTENDED in emergency situations (i.e. shipside emergencies).

## Detainment Authority
  The follow regulations apply in the regards of Command ordering detainment or being detained.
    - All orders from the detained command personnel are null and void, and shall not be followed by anyone.
    - Command may not order the arrest of someone on grounds of suspicion
    - Command may not pardon anyone of a crime, unless for the sakes of an emergency, this does not apply to Capital crimes, or violent crimes (i.e. Murder)
    - The CMO may order arrests on the grounds of Insanity if done so after a proper examination with documentation. Under no other circumstances shall a person be ordered to be arrested for Insanity.

## Do Not Revive Orders
  The follow regulations apply for DNR orders issued by MPs or Command
    - DNRs may not be issued by the XO or CO without proper documentation received from NEMO or HighComm.
    - CO or XO may request for a DNR through NEMO or HighComm.
    - If a person requests a DNR from the CMO for themselves and it is approved, it must be followed by law, chargeable by VoL (major crimes).
    - DNRs can be issued after a person or persons is tried through court and found guilty and then issued a DNR and/or execution.

 ## Field Arrests
These refer to arrests performed in the area of operations.
  - Anyone may detain personnel of their faction that commit a major or capital crime, but must detain personnel of their faction by orders of the MP/Law Enforcement, commander, or any officer.
  - Anyone may detain personnel deploying unauthorized, even without orders to do so.
  - Personnel detained should be passed onto the MP/Law Enforcement or an Officer in a secure area when possible.
  - MPs/Law Enforcement MAY leave the FOB to detain or arrest members of their faction who have committed any offense that is not minor or optional, but must disengage and return to the FOB if attacked by anyone other than the suspect they are pursuing.
</Document>
