<Document>
  # GENERAL PROVISIONS

  ## BASICS
  - All persons within colony jurisdiction must obey colonial law and follow lawful safety orders during emergencies, evacuations, quarantines, and security events.
  - Colony Marshals and Administration may use discretion on minor offenses unless ordered otherwise by higher authority. Law Enforcement may not have their own offenses ignored.
  - Proportional self-defense is legal. Force should be reasonable for the threat faced.
  - No person may serve more than 25 minutes in holding unless placed under permanent confinement.
  - Execution is never legal or sanctioned.
  - Permanent confinement is reserved for extreme threats to colony safety or persons who cannot be safely released.
  - Colonial law is civilian law. Military procedure does not apply unless martial law is lawfully declared.

  ## CIVILIAN LEGAL AUTHORITY
  Civilian Court / Arbiter > Administrator > Chief Marshal > Colony Marshals > Deputized Security

  - If a civilian court is active, it has final authority over criminal cases.
  - If no court is active, the Marshal's Office handles arrests, charges, and sentencing.
  - Colonial and corporate administrators may issue lawful civil, safety, and emergency directives. Corporate policy does not override colonial criminal law.
  - Law Enforcement may refuse unlawful orders.

  ## COURTS AND LEGAL REVIEW
  Most offenses are processed directly by the Marshal's Office. A formal court may be convened for major/capital crimes, disputed arrests, abuse of authority, corporate misconduct, or matters of public concern.

  Court proceedings may involve a judge (e.g. Arbiter or Administator), prosecutor, legal counsel, witnesses, and evidence review. Outcomes may include charges upheld, reduced, or dismissed; sentences adjusted; property returned; or licenses suspended/restored.

  Legal counsel is not guaranteed but may be appointed for major or disputed cases. Court rulings are final unless overruled by Colonial High Authority.
</Document>
