<Document>
  # Dropships and Aircraft

  These regulations govern the authority, modification and operational use of all aircraft and dropships.

  ## Flight Crew Authority
  - The Pilot(s) are responsible for their assigned aircraft and any modifications made to them.
  - Pilot(s) may modify their aircraft without requesting permission.
  - These modifications may not be overridden by the Acting Commander.
  - Flight Crew have final authority over who is permitted aboard their aircraft.
  - Flight Crew may remove personnel of any rank from their aircraft for any reason.

  ## Aircraft Integrity
  - Dismantling aircraft components to obtain materials for other purposes is strictly forbidden.
  - Ship doors must remain intact at all times.
  - Ship doors may not be tampered in a way that causes them to remain INOP in flight (i.e. bolting them open then taking off.)

  ## Seating and Cargo
  - Seating capacity may be reduced to accommodate additional ammunition or cargo.
  - Seating may not be completely removed on the primary dropship, seating may be completely removed on the Gunship if it is NOT the only operatable ship.

  ## Primary Transport Role
  - If a dropship becomes inaccessible or inoperable, another aircraft must assume the transport role.
  - The replacement aircraft must be configured with appropriate troop seating whenever possible.

  ## Parachute Operations
  - When conducting parachute drops, Flight Crew are responsible for:
    - Ensuring the drop zone is safe.
    - Notifying personnel when to deploy.
    - Ensuring that they are not deploying troops into an active firefight for safety reasons.
    - Blind Drops are forbidden unless the operating platoon is a certified para-operations platoon (i.e. RMC, USCM, and UPP)

  ## Purchasing of Munitions
  - When Purchasing Munitions for the dropship, Flight Crew may only:
    - Spend 20% of the budget freely (rounding down to nearest whole number, i.e. 2109.77 is 2109). Anymore then this falls under the approval of the LO, if none is present the Tech. If the installitation grants a DP access to their own purchases, violators may be charged with NUR and FTFP
    - May request any munition at anytime as long as it does not conflict with the first regulation.
    - Are responsible for the transportation of all their munitions, but may REQUEST (not order) assistance from Technicians or other staff authorized to use a powerloader.

</Document>
