<Document>
  # Equipment and Personnel Standards

  These are sets of regulations and policies that govern the use of equipment and standards of appearance for military personnel.

  ## Standard Issue Equipment
  - Standard issue equipment is defined as any military or police uniform, armor, weapon, or accessory personnel find in their vendors, as well as anything they awake with or anything normally available from requisitions or respective armory(s).
  - The Acting Commander may issue special equipment on a case by case basis, such as special headsets or special weaponry for certain personnel or units as long as it does not violate the UCMJ or a specific ban as stated in SOP
  - Alcohol must be stored in the officer's mess or an officer's office(s).

  ## Uniform Regulations
  Personnel are required to be wearing appropriate clothing during operations. SOP may not be changed to allow personnel to deploy without clothes or uniform.
  - Deploying personnel must be wearing their uniform, boots and chest protective armor at minimum. Suit webbings may be used in the place of chest protective armor.
  - All positions required to wear armor at all times may temporarily remove it while on a friendly ship and/or installation or after an operation has ended for social events, such as memorials. Other forms of clothing like service jackets may be used during this time.
  - All personnel must wear their uniform and assigned footwear, or a standard issue replacement.
  - Auxiliary staff and support crew should not be in armor unless the ship/base is on a security alert, or are deploying to the AO.
  - MP/Law Enforcement, combat personnel and flight crew are permitted to wear armor on the ship/installation, as part of their job.
  - Any headwear that is worn must be standard issue, or an acceptable replacement. Exceptions must be made for reasonable religious headdress
  - Anyone of higher rank may still order any personnel below them to wear a protective helmet or vest unless they are a rifleman who has not been issued a special weapon.
  - Folding or otherwise shortening uniforms is permitted, provided no damage comes to the uniform.

  ## Firearm Handling Regulations
  - Weapons should be holstered or slung when not in use and on safety. Personnel must be allowed to holster or sling on their first offense.
  - Under normal circumstances, weapons may only be fired in the firing range. (Unless for cermonial purposes)
  - Training equipment like training grenades and training ammunition must only be used in firing ranges.
  - Weapons may not be left unattended unless properly secured in spaces intended for them, like weapon racks or cabinets.
  - If no firing range is available MPs may be asked to designate a temporary safe area for weapons to be discharged.

  ## Synthetic Operations
  - Synthetics are not at any point authorized to weild a firearm, synths may hold firearms in one hand for transport or safety reasons.
  - Synthetics are allowed to carry knives, tools, and other simillar equipment if needed to function in their job at optimal levels.
  - Synthetics may conduct arrests but are not allowed to sentence due to not being able to understand spirit of law. If MP or CMP is available, the Synth may sentence.
  - Synthetics designed for specified tasks shall be expected to conduct those tasks with minimal supervision, if a synthtic is assigned a task outside their defined purpose in their user manual, they shall be supervised by an experinced personnel.
  - Synthetics used in a combat capacity must be monitored 24/7, if remotely monitored if any connection failure is to occur the synthetic shall be declared rogue and marked shoot to kill until a reset is performed fully.
  - Syntethics may be sent to their manufacturer for examination if a represenitive or alike is on or near installiation. If the units user manual says not to allow access by other companies, it must be respected.
  - Synthetics may be dismissed from the current position if ordered by the Department Head of their specialization (General use synthetics may only be dismissed by CO or XO)
  - Synthetics may perform operations alone, but should not be sent off installiation for longer then 10 minutes unsupervised.

  ## Grooming Standards
  - Personnel must maintain a professional and operationally safe hairstyle while on duty.
  - Hair may be worn down to the shoulders in a bob or similar style, but must be tied back if it extends any longer.
  - Tied-back hair, such as ponytails, may extend to the small of the back but must not exceed that length or wrap around to the front.
  - Facial hair is permitted but must not extend below the neckline or past the face in any direction.
  - Hair must be of a natural color.
  - Synthetic units are exempt, unless their users manual states otherwise

  [italic]OOC Note: Character appearance is a significant part of roleplay and can greatly impact a player's experience. For this reason, if you choose to enforce grooming standards, you must allow the player to either adjust their own hairstyle or choose a new one for themselves. If they deny any hair style AHelp an admin for advice [/italic]

  ## Vehicle and Motorized Assets
  If a vehicle or other general motorized asset is deployed for any reason the following regulations apply
  - Authority of the vehicle falls under the on duty Vehicle Commander, and then to be operated by the Vehicle Crew. If no Vehicle Commander or Crew is present it falls under the Engineering Officer
  - Only Technicians may operate APC's, Tanks, IFV, and simillar vehicles.
  - Humvees are exempt and may be assigned to a sqaud for use by the sqaud, the assignment being ordered by the XO or CO, if it is not assigned humvees automatically fall under Vehicle Crew assignment
  - Medical assets fall under the jurisdiciton of the Chief Medical Officer. If no CMO is available it falls to the above stated jurisdicitons.
  - If a vehicle is to become INOP or unsafe for use it is to be returned to the installiation and may only be redeployed if authorized by an EO.

</Document>
