<Document>
  # MAJOR CRIMES

  ## Disorderly Conduct
  Severely disrupting colony operations, emergency response, or essential services (blocking emergency response, interfering with evacuation, causing panic during emergency operations, disrupting medical triage).
  - 10 min

  ## Assault
  Threatening or using physical force with hostile intent.
  - 10 min unarmed | 15 min with a deadly weapon

  ## Manslaughter
  Killing someone without malicious intent due to reckless or negligent conduct.
  - 20 min + possible license revocation, job removal, or permanent confinement if the person remains a danger

  ## Illegal Confinement
  Unlawfully restraining, kidnapping, or imprisoning another person. Does not apply to lawful quarantine, arrest, or protective custody.
  - 20 min

  ## Major Theft
  Stealing colony funds, emergency supplies, weapons, vehicles, access cards, or restricted equipment.
  - 15 min + return of property

  ## Unauthorized Access to Corporate Property
  Accessing company equipment, labs, records, or restricted areas without authorization.
  - 7 min (minor access) | 15 min if restricted materials, vehicles, records, or systems are involved

  ## Misuse of Colony Infrastructure
  Improperly operating, disabling, or modifying colony systems (atmosphere processors, reactor systems, airlocks, water processors, emergency shelters, fuel systems).
  - 15 min | 20 min if public safety endangered | Permanent confinement if mass death or colony collapse risk

  ## Sabotage
  Damaging, disabling, or compromising colony infrastructure, utilities, or safety/security systems.
  - 20 min | Permanent confinement if the act creates mass danger

  ## Possession of Restricted Contraband
  Possessing restricted drugs, military equipment, explosives, illegal weapons, classified material, or dangerous organisms.
  - 15-20 min + confiscation

  ## Unauthorized Distress Signal
  Sending a distress call, emergency beacon, or evacuation signal without lawful authorization.
  - 15 min | 20 min if it causes panic, military deployment, or operational disruption

  ## Interference with Emergency Response
  Obstructing marshals, medical staff, evacuation crews, or other lawful emergency responders.
  - 15 min | 20 min if injury, death, contamination, or major delay results

  ## Biohazard Noncompliance
  Refusing lawful quarantine, decontamination, medical screening, or isolation procedures.
  - 20 min | Permanent confinement if the violation risks outbreak, mass infection, or colony‑wide contamination

  ## Possession of Restricted Biological Material
  Possessing, hiding, transporting, or selling dangerous biological material without authorization (unknown eggs, parasitic organisms, pathogen samples, infected tissue, invasive lifeform remains, unknown organic material from restricted zones).
  - 20 min + confiscation/destruction + mandatory quarantine | Permanent confinement if colony safety endangered

  ## Harboring a Contaminated Person
  Knowingly hiding or assisting a person under quarantine or suspected of carrying a dangerous pathogen.
  - 20 min | Permanent confinement if outbreak risk is created

  ## Corporate Espionage
  Stealing, copying, or transmitting restricted corporate, scientific, or biological research data.
  - 20 min | Permanent confinement if tied to hostile powers, terrorist groups, or hazardous biological research

  ## Unauthorized Disclosure
  Releasing restricted colony, scientific, military, or biological information without authorization.
  - 10 min (minor) | 20 min if it causes panic or operational disruption | Permanent confinement if mass casualties or colony collapse risk

  ## Corruption
  Using public, law enforcement, or administrative authority for personal gain or unlawful punishment.
  - 15 min + removal from position

  ## Abuse of Authority
  Issuing unlawful arrests, searches, seizures, administrative orders, or emergency directives.
  - 15 min + removal from position

  ## Harboring a Fugitive
  Knowingly hiding or assisting a person wanted for a major or capital crime.
  - 15 min

  ## Rioting
  Participating in violent public unrest involving property damage, assault, theft, arson, or obstruction of emergency services.
  - 20 min
</Document>
