<Document>
  #INSURGENCY RULES
    These rules apply to the Insurgency gamemode.

  ##General Rules
    No player may kill another player within the first 5 minutes of the round.

    Colonists and other non-affiliated roles must have a valid in-character reason to participate in hostilities.

    ##Insurgent Rules

    You are a radical devoted to your cause.
    - Direct orders from the Cell Leader must be followed unless they directly contradict insurgent ideology or server rules. You must refuse orders to indiscriminately kill civilians.

    Insurgents may not kill or harm civilians unless they are clearly hostile toward the insurgency.
    - Ambassadors, liaisons, administrators and other unarmed government/corporate personnel are considered civilians under this rule.
    - Colony Law Enforcement, Corporate Security and armed government/corporate personnel are not considered civilians under this rule.

    Insurgents may NOT kill or harm Colony Law Enforcement, Corporate Security and/or armed government/corporate personnel until 10 minutes into the round.

    Insurgents may NOT attack groundside GOVFOR bases or attempt to board the GOVFOR ship until 30 minutes into the round. FOBs are not considered groundside bases.

    ##GOVFOR Rules

    GOVFOR may not enter the colony unless:
    - They are explicitly alerted by the Colony Command
    - 30 minutes have passed since round start.
    - If GOVFOR spawn on a ship, they may deploy to their primary LZ and secure an FOB before the thirty minute mark, but must not leave their FOB.

    GOVFOR may not shoot civilians without reasonable cause such as:
    - Ignoring one clear warnings to leave while in sight.
    - Wearing or possessing illegal firearms or equipment.
    - Being reported to be carrying explosives.
    - They are using lethal force or you have seen them use lethal force.

    GOVFOR may not raid an insurgent base unless:
    - They are actively following an insurgent member to it.
    - They have received credible intelligence about its location.

    ##Colony Command Rules

    A valid in-character reason is required to request GOVFOR assistance such as:
    - Insurgents openly carrying illegal weapons.
    - Law Enforcement or multiple civilians being killed.
    - Explicit IC death threats.
    - An attempt on the life of a colony command member.
</Document>