<Document>

  # Medical V2

  ## Overview
  - The medical system has heavily changed.
  - Patients now suffer specific wounds on their limbs.
  - Wounds reduce the maximum health of the affected limb until they are cleaned up.
  - Healing wounds with the optimal treatment restores the limb's maximum health.

  ## Inspecting injuries
  - For a detailed report, right click a patient and choose [bold]Inspect injuries[/bold].
  - You can also use [keybind="CMUInspectInjuries"] while targeting the patient.
  - The report lists their wounds and the optimal treatment needed for each one.

  ## Field treatment crafting
  - Use [keybind="CMUOpenMedicalCraftingMenu"] to fast craft medical treatments.
  - Crafting uses one ingredient and one base item.
  - The two packed base items are packed gauze and packed trauma kits.
  - Normal medical gauze and trauma kits can also be used as base items.

  ## Ingredients
  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUCoagulantPowder1"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUAntiseptic1"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUBurnGel1"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUTissueSealant1"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUTraumaFoam1"/>
  </Box>\n

  ## Base items
  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUPlainGauze10"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUPlainTraumaDressing10"/>
  </Box>
  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMGauze10"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMTraumaKit10"/>
  </Box>\n

  ## Optimal treatments
  - Bullet, stab, fragment, ballistic, and sharp wounds need a hemostatic dressing made with coagulant powder.
  - Contaminated wounds and dirty dressings need an antiseptic dressing made with antiseptic.
  - Burns and charred tissue need a burn gel dressing made with burn gel.
  - Slashes, surgical wounds, and poor closure need a sealing dressing made with tissue sealant.
  - Crush, blast, and crush-debris wounds need a compression dressing made with trauma foam.
  - Retained fragments must have the shrapnel removed before the correct dressing can finish the cleanup.

  ## Adequate treatment
  - If a marine is [bold]adequately treated[/bold], another bandage already stopped or covered the wound.
  - Adequate treatment is not optimal treatment.
  - Apply the correct treatment from the injury report to clean the wound up and restore the lost maximum limb health.

  ## Surgical line and synth graft
  - Surgical line now heals limb health only.
  - Synth graft now heals limb health only.
  - Neither item cleans up wounds or restores maximum limb health by itself.
  - Use the correct crafted treatment for wounds, then use line or graft when the limb still needs health.

</Document>
